so obviously with the advent of the you
know so-called intellectual dark web and
the idea that there are many public into
intellectuals yourself included
that have been experiencing both height
and prominence and controversy as we
have kind of tried to wade into the
culture wars and identity politics and
all of the things that sort of have
wrapped the the Western world around the
axle lately what is your sense both of
why that is happening now
what are potentially some of the sort of
evolutionary reasons for it and then
also I mean and then let's try and
explore together what's next we are
built for the various canonical
obstacles that we face in evolutionary
history or we have faced what we don't
realize is that we carry many latent
programs for alternative circumstances
programs that we may never encounter if
the circumstances that they match never
show up in our environment I would argue
that one of these is for periods of
austerity that in a period of economic
contraction or its pre economic
equivalent people go into a phase that's
very tribal and they start looking
around and thinking who's vulnerable who
can't defend their stuff my people can
afford to be a lot nicer to each other
when there's plenty to go around because
of growth or its equivalent but when
that Peters out people start going after
each other and we're in a very confusing
phase because one of the things that
tells you that you're in an economic
contraction is just not enough food and
we don't face that situation so in a
sense even though we are in a
contraction one of the signals that
would cause people to go tribal has been
suspended but others are beginning to
kick in and there is a general sense in
our culture that things are coming apart
and that sense that things are coming
apart have people looking for a kind of
higher ground that will involve
tribalism and will involve people doing
things that violate the values they
believe they hold and I think that's
what we're seeing
you either can move forward to kind of a
more global perspective like we are all
connected in some way or you can regress
so it's progress or regress back to us
know centric tribalism and obviously as
we Teeter on this brink of saying hey
the problems we face these days are no
longer national they don't stop at
borders whether it's refugees or climate
or geopolitics or macroeconomics they
they are complex ambiguous and
transnational wish that it feels like
we're being dragged into a global
central awareness but it's also the
transitional period - and just one more
metaphor and mix it a little bit like
being a soft-shell crab
you know we've left the confining shell
of nationalism and tribalism
we are absolutely vulnerable in this
transition and people are you know
there's not necessarily a clear voice of
leadership to get us all through that
transition and into the more expansive
container of we are all in this together
so you have a lot of demagogues right
and a lot of kind of so-called populism
saying come back into the old shells you
know divide rather than unite and I
would just add that one thing you can do
once you realize that that pattern is
there is recognized that where this ends
is not good unless we intervene so in
other words this pattern of there's
abundance abundance leads to certain
kinds of willingness to interact
broad-mindedness let's say then there's
contraction and austerity and that
results in a kind of tribalism this
oscillation is going to kill us the
solution to it
the solution to it involves architecting
a stable a steady state that gives us
the inputs of abundance in a way that
does not oscillate between boom and bust
if you can create it looks like a world
in which people have enough they have
the sense that things are getting better
because you've architected them to give
people that sense of breadth in other
words maybe you have shifted growth into
a different mode in other words if
everybody is freed to be generative so
you're constantly encountering new
interesting stuff
that feels like the world of abundance
that happens when you've just discovered
some concentrated source of growth
it may not be predicated on growth and
that's the point is we're not in a
position as human beings to track actual
growth so if we can substitute things
that feel like growth then we will put
people into their growth mindset as it
were and then they can't afford and they
will naturally be inclined to be decent
to each other what you're describing
seems you know beautiful possible but
wildly ambitious and we take a hell of a
long time if it worked at all I mean
like you are you talking about like a
fundamental retooling of socio-economic
structures and national stories and
pervasive messaging and public sentiment
all to the point where people like oh
yes we can afford to be generous we can
afford to be kind we can afford to be
inclusive I'm talking about a process
that will take three generations at
least okay do we have that much time
well let's put it this way you don't
need to solve the entire problem at once
you need to forestall the existential
threats none of them can come to
fruition if this project is to work so
we have to wake up to those things that
threaten us acutely and we have to begin
addressing them that does not have to
happen in exactly the same moment as
people begin to feel a steady-state
abundance but you do have to give them a
burst of abundance in order to relax the
tribalism that is setting in so the
question is how do we get enough people
to have a post global experience in
order to annex global centric
perspective and the only two options I
can think of is either one independence
day level stuff the discovery of other
life something that really wakes us up
to the fact that we are here together on
this little blue marble and that's and
that's the sort of search the
astronaut's the the other is the you
know or some form of Psychonauts some
form of expansion in consciousness that
you could scale rapidly relatively
speaking within the span of a generation
that gives people a post conventional
global perspective in their interiors
such that when we get back to start
doing your longer a bigger harder
project there are people who are
actually holding that that beat there's
several
to the place you're talking about none
of them are easy but they're relatively
straightforward one thing is the fact
that we have become an existential
threat to ourselves slots in very nicely
to the enemy that we face together all
right we've seen the enemy it is us and
so that awareness of that can I believe
trigger the kind of unity that you're
talking about the problem is that
narrative which I believe is true we
have become the existential threat to
ourselves that narrative is in conflict
with those who are most powerful in
civilization who would like to keep it
running as it is because it's feeding
them pretty darn well so that story even
though it should unify us it happens
that there are a few holdouts and
they're the most powerful people and
they're selling a different story and
also she feels like it requires a degree
of radical self assessment to say it is
us not to say it is them right the
natural tendency is to see it as them
but it is really it is us it is the
processes that you know somehow keep
this room temperate you know they're
fueled by some power station somewhere
that has implications so you know it is
really us it's the processes that we are
depending on that we don't see day to
day but they're out there the other
thing and you know and you you point to
it I think you called it the psychonaut
route into that sort of unity involves
an Enlightenment and awakening to a deep
truth and I the analogy I use as this if
you discovered that you were a robot and
that you were sent to I don't know
assassinate some person who was innocent
if you discovered that that was the
explanation for you you would reject
your program right you as the robot that
had been given decency in order to get
by everybody so you could commit your
assassination would say actually I
prioritize the values and I reject the
mission that I've been sent on that's
who we are we are that robot we are on a
genetic mission that is absolutely
unacceptable how would you how you just
succinctly define that genetic mission
that genetic mission just propagation
and all
propagation of your particular genetic
Spelling's and here's the key it's a
little subtle but if you and I have
different spellings for a particular
let's say a respiratory enzyme and let's
say that respiratory enzyme functions
better in you than in me it's ten
percent more efficient my respiratory
enzyme still wants your respiratory
enzyme to go extinct because it doesn't
care about the function it cares that
that spelling is advanced and your
spelling is in conflict with my spelling
as long as yours is around there will be
fewer copies of mine so our genomes are
actually interested I mean that if I can
just be clear about it the mindfuck of
the whole thing is that the entire
evolutionary story
is the cosmic spelling bee and it ends
in genocide right once you realize that
that's what you are that you're built to
advance your genetic Spelling's into the
future generations irrespective of what
they spell and that under circumstances
like these we can afford to be decent to
each other but if things were different
one of us would be putting the other in
a gas chamber no way I want no part of
that and neither do you
so when people realize that that's
really what they are they are built to
be nice when it makes sense to be nice
and they're built to be Jenna Seidel in
circumstances when genocide is the thing
then the question is well all the things
that you actually value how consistent
are they with being that robot on that
mission so it sounds like you are sort
of saying at our route we are nasty
brutish and short the old selfish gene
kind of thing compared to some
essentialist or triumphal s clearly you
know it's very prevalent in the
self-help popular psychology space we
are on the frothy edge of realizing our
true natures as you know spiritual
beings blah Blee blah is that something
you don't hold out hope for you feel
like at root we are just self oriented
robot programs is what's what's our shot
at redemption that one it's easier it's
easier than you would think
because the fact is I'm telling you we
are that robot on that mission once you
know that that's your mission you could
just reject it all right I'm not I'm not
putting anybody in a gas
I just won't do it alright I don't care
about the genetic Spelling's at all and
I really don't if I discovered that my
sons were switched in the hospital at
birth and they were not actually related
to me it doesn't change my relationship
to them it doesn't affect whether I love
them I don't love them because they're
genetic Spelling's so my point is we are
actually evolution screwed up it handed
us the tools to recognize that we don't
have to value the game that it is
playing and that we can now repurpose
the hardware to something that's
actually worthwhile and how liberating
is that I mean who wants to walk around
with bigotry yeah I mean it's funny cuz
I mean that was just in my next book
there's gonna be a section evolution is
a moral and there's and no sooner do you
realise that that you realized oh we are
being nudged pushed and prodded into a
whole lot of outcomes that create tons
of pain in our psychosocial frameworks
our value sets that are 100% wins on the
evolutionary level yeah and tragic for
us right and the the crazy thing is
freedom from that is as close as just
recognizing what it is and then saying
well I mean I have a particular analogy
I like there's this point at which pilot
the pilot's name was Sully I guess
captain Sully who landed the the plane
on the Hudson is a point at which the
birds have struck the engines and he
needs to land the plane on the water and
there's a good chance that he's gonna
kill everybody on board but their best
chance that they're gonna live is him
right
and he says my aircraft which is what
you say when you take it away from the
autopilot alright you take
responsibility for it and the basic
point is we need to look at evolution
and we need to say my aircraft all right
it's that simple